Nicole: So, what exactly is bias?
Bias is the inclination or prejudice
for or against something or someone.
We all have biases that often
impact our decisions, and this
also goes for cyber security.
Abraham: Cyber security personnel have
to address what alerts to investigate,
what systems to patch and often these
decisions are affected by biases
which help us to react more quickly.
Nicole: Imagine if the current threat
landscape shows a high level of breaches
by foreign hackers, then cyber security
teams might be on the lookout for these
and may miss the more common internal
or localised social engineering threat.
Abraham: Threat actors use this bias to
try to exploit and threaten our security.
By being aware of bias and how it
can affect our decision making, it
can help us to avoid making mistakes.
Nicole: Let’s have a look at some of
the different types of bias and how
they may affect cyber security issues:
Cognitive Bias is the result of
the brains attempt to simplify
information processing; we create
our own subjective reality due
to our perception of the input.
We may see or hear something but
perceive the information differently to
someone , even though the information
we both receive is the same.
Abraham: It is therefore important
to discuss things with others to see
their point of view on the situation.
Availability Bias is a mental
shortcut based on past examples
relating to the available information.
If we are used to hearing this
information, then we recall it quickly
and therefore it can influence our
‘go to’ solution and as such, if
a problem was in a specific area
previously, we might automatically
feel that it is the same again, rather
than looking at the bigger picture.
Nicole: Availability bias is also
evident when an organisation prepares for
‘high impact’ ‘low probability events’
instead of ‘high probability’ events.
High probability events should
be mostly prepared for as they
are more likely to happen!
Abraham: Confirmation Bias is when
more attention is paid to things that
confirm your own beliefs rather than
looking for other points of view.
Nicole: Imagine investigating a
data breach by a suspected malicious
employee, then that is the evidence you
would be looking for and subsequently
you might miss the real cause.
Abraham: Implicit or Unconscious Bias
can influence our bias by believing
in the experts especially if you
already have an association with them.
If they think it’s right, then it
must be, without even challenging the
data and looking at alternative views.
Nicole: Being on the side of the
majority is not always the best approach.
You should look at the facts and then make
your own decisions and if they differ from
others identify, then look at why this is.
Abraham: In cyber security
there may often be assumptions
made about users due to bias.
This may involve an age approach
which could follows the adage
‘older and wiser’ or conversely
older therefore ‘not up to date’.
Nicole: Younger people can also be
seen as more knowledgeable of new
technology, but may be reckless and
likely to get involved in risky behaviour.
Both ends of the spectrum can be
right for various reasons but how
we perceive things is more often
than not, related to our bias.
Abraham: Cyber security professionals
need to always investigate with
an open mind and not automatically
think that the user is to blame.
To tackle this bias the cyber security
professional should go beyond the user and
see if the system is to blame, ultimately
making it much easier for accidents
to happen after all no one is perfect.